Finding Aid for Office of Lesbian Gay Bisexual and Transgender Affairs (University of Michigan) Records, 1976-2001
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Office of Lesbian Gay Bisexual and Transgender Affairs (University of Michigan) Records1976-2005 1988-1997
University of Michigan. Office of Lesbian Gay Bisexual and Transgender Affairs.
02139 Bimu B7 2
University of Michigan office dealing with human sexuality issues for students, faculty and staff. Records consist of administrative and topical files of the Office of LGBT Affairs and its predecessor offices, relating to the operation of the office, outreach programs, advocacy efforts, and background on university housing issues, same sex benefits, as well as local, state and national issues pertaining to gay and lesbian rights. Documentation also includes posters, photos and audio-visual material.
6 linear feet
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Transferred from Office of Lesbian Gay Bisexual and Transgender Affairs in 1998 and 2001 (donor no. 8742 ).
The records are open to research except for the Ted Fredley Files series (Box 6) which is closed.
The Office of Lesbian Gay Bisexual and Transgender Affairs (LGBTA) was created in 1971 as the Human Sexuality Office within the Office of Special Services and Programs of the University of Michigan. Initially heading the office were two individuals, a lesbian advocate and a gay male advocate, each of them temporary and part-time. A year later the advocate positions were upgraded to permanent and professional level, but they were still only funded at one-quarter time. Five years later the advocates became funded at one-half time through the efforts of concerned university and community members. In 1980, the office was taken out of the Office of Special Services and Programs and brought under the supervision of the Director of Counseling Services. At this same time, the term advocate was dropped and in its place the position of program coordinator established. By the late 1980s the co-coordinator positions were made full-time. In 1994, the office ceased having two individuals in charge (one for lesbians and one for gay males) and a single director headed the program. Ronni Sanlo served as the first director. It was also at this time that James W. Toy resigned as Gay Male Advocate. Toy was instrumental in the establishment of the office and had served as the Gay Male Advocate for twenty-three years. Over the years, the program has changed its name several times, from the Human Sexuality Office to the Lesbian-Gay Male Programs Office (LGMPO), to the Lesbian-Gay Male-Bisexual Programs Office, to its current title. The office is administratively located within the office of the Associate Dean of Students in the Office of Students Affairs.
As the first such university office established in the United States, the Human Sexuality Office had no models to emulate. The diverse program created by the two advocates was intended to meet specific needs and concerns. From the beginning education, peer advising and counseling, gay rights advocacy, and community organization were the primary concerns of the Human Sexuality Office. Throughout the history of the office, the advocates sought to educate the university community to dispel myths and stereotypes about gay life. Through classroom presentations, appearances at seminars and conferences, both within and outside the university environment, and consciousness-raising sessions for university units, the office sought to promote an open and supportive environment at the university. The popularity and demand for such presentations soon overwhelmed the advocates and they began a program to train volunteers or facilitators who would go around to the various classes. This emphasis of was designated the Educational Outreach Program and was eventually headed, beginning in 1982, by paid coordinators. Additionally, LGMPO served as a clearinghouse where gay men and lesbians could go for information about gay life and activities.
The counseling program of the office consisted of peer and professional counseling and peer counselor and group facilitator training. The advocates were able to provide short- and long-term professional counseling for individuals, couples, and groups. For a time, the office became home to a 24-hour "Gay Hotline" operated by members of the Gay Liberation Front (GLF) and funded privately by the GLF and others. The Hotline served those individuals, sometimes troubled, who needed to talk with someone of a similar sexual orientation or who could be referred to an appropriate organization or individual with specialized professional training.
Gay rights advocacy was a core mission of the office. Beginning in 1972, one of the important aims of the advocates was working towards an amendment of Regents Bylaw 14.06 to prohibit discrimination within the university community based on sexual orientation. Much of the first public demonstration to revise 14.06 was done by the Gay Liberation Front and then in the 1980s by a student group known as LaGROC (Lesbian and Gay Rights on Campus). Using sit-ins and other non-violent demonstrations, LaGROC dramatized the importance of revising the bylaw. In 1984, pressure from LaGROC was primarily responsible for President Harold Shapiro issuing a Presidential Policy on non-discrimination. Although sexual orientation was still not included as part of 14.06 (the Bylaw was eventually changed in September 1993), the presidential statement was a partial victory for LaGROC, and led to the establishment of the President's Task Force on Sexual Orientation that was intended to oversee the implementation of the Presidential Policy.
The office celebrated its thirtieth anniversary (Fall 2002) under the direction of Frederic MacDonald-Dennis. The office offers a variety of educational and training opportunities, events, as well as resources housed in the Jim Toy Library and Resource Center.
The records of the Office of Lesbian Gay Bisexual and Transgender Affairs (LGBTA) document the activities of the Office from 1976 to 2001, but mainly cover the period from 1989 to 1997. For earlier records of the office see the Lesbian-Gay Male-Bisexual Programs Office series within the James W. Toy collection, which is also held at the Bentley Library. Note that there is some overlap between the records in the Toy collection and this record group.
The record group contain correspondence including electronic mail printouts, memoranda, clippings, educational training manuals, photographic, and audio and visual materials. The records are organized in three series: Administrative Files, Topical Files and Audio-Visual Material.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Office of Lesbian Gay Bisexual and Transgender Affairs.; Bisexual college students--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Gay college students--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Gays--Michigan.; Homosexuality--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Lesbians--Michigan.; Sexual orientation--Michigan.; Transsexual college students--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan. Human Sexuality Office.; University of Michigan. Task Force on Sexual Orientation.; University of Michigan. Lesbian-Gay Male Program Office.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
University of Michigan. Office of Lesbian Gay Bisexual and Transgender Affairs.; Gay rights--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Gays--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Demonstrations--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Coming out (Sexual orientation)--Michigan.; Sexual orientation--Michigan.; Lesbians--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Toy, James W., 1930-
Genre Terms:
Videotapes.; Photographs.
- Administrative Files
  - Executive Files
    The series Administrative Files, 1987-1999 (2 linear feet) is divided into two subseries: Executive Files and Office Files. The executive files contain correspondence and other material created or directed to the office co-coordinator, Billie Edwards or after 1994 to the Director, Ronni Sanlo. Sanlo was the first person to hold the position of Director of the office. The Office Files subseries contains general office correspondence ca. 1991-1997, staff meeting minutes and agendas, material related to the President's New Century Fund Award for Diversity for work on the report "From Invisibility to Inclusion" project, and a number of files related to the Task Force on Sexual Orientation. The task force materials range in date from 1987 to 1991. Note that the James W. Toy collection, boxes 8 and 9, also contains material related to the Task Force on Sexual Orientation.
    - Correspondence, incoming 1988-1992, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, outgoing 1988-1992, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Electronic Mail (printouts) 1991-1992 (Box 1)
    - Ronni Sanlo Files
      - Electronic Mail Correspondence 1994, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - Electronic Mail Correspondence 1994-1995, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - General Files 1994-1996, 11 folders (Box 1)
      - Search Committee for Director 1993-1994 (Box 1)
  - Office Files
    - Awards and Certificates 1991-1996 (Box 1)
    - Budget Memos 1991-1995, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Calendar of Events
      - 1997 (Box 1)
      - 1998 (Box 1)
    - Contact and Referral Lists 1987-1991 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, general 1991-1997, 4 folders (Box 1)
    - Lesbian Gay Men Projects Office (LGMPO)
      - Advisory Committee 1993, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - Correspondence, miscellaneous 1992-1993 (Box 1)
      - General files 1993-1994, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - Program Planning 1991 (Box 1)
      - Review of Programs Office 1991-1993, 2 folders (Box 1)
        (includes electronic mail printouts)
    - Mission and Goals 1994 (Box 2)
    - Notes on the "Rainbow Tour" Washington D.C. 1996 (Box 2)
    - President's New Century Fund for Diversity
      - Award and background materials 1992-1999 (Box 2)
      - PowerPoint presentation circa 1999 (Box 2)
    - Program on Intergroup Relations and Conflict 1995, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Review of Lesbian Gay Male Program 1991-1993 (Box 2)
    - Staff Meetings
      - Minutes 1991-1992 (Box 2)
      - Agendas 1994-1995 (Box 2)
    - Student Task Force on Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual Issues 1993, 3 folders (Box 2)
      (includes e-mail printouts)
    - Study Committee on the Status of Lesbians and Gay Men
      - Final Report, From Invisibility to Inclusion: Opening the Doors for Lesbians and Gay Men at the University of Michigan 1991 (Box 2)
      - Survey Distribution 1990 (Box 2)
      - Survey Responses 1990, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Task Force on Sexual Orientation
      - 1987, 3 folders (Box 2)
      - 1988-1989, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Task Force on Sexual Orientation (Box 3)
      - 1988-1989, 1 folders (Box 3)
      - 1988-1991, 6 folders (Box 3)
      - Bibliography and Non-Discrimination Policy Survey 1989-1990 (Box 3)
    - Visitor Information and Phone Log 1995 (Box 3)
- Topical Files
  The Topical Files series, 1976-2001 (1.75 linear feet) contains a number of folders arranged by subject relating to human sexuality and gay, lesbian, bisexual and transgender rights activities. This series includes background materials on housing issues at the university, same-sex benefits, and printouts of the LGBTA online newsletter from the years 1995 to 1997. The series includes an office clippings file ca. 1989-1999 that is arranged by coverage at the university, within Ann Arbor, and within the State of Michigan. The series also contains a small amount of material related to the Educational Outreach Program dating from the early 1990s. A significant amount of educational outreach material can be found in the James W. Toy Collection boxes 2-5.
  - Bisexual Men's Group 1994 (Box 3)
  - Bisexual Women's Social Group 1992-1994 (Box 3)
  - Clippings File
    - Issues in Ann Arbor
      - 1991-1996 (Box 3)
      - 1998-1999 (Box 3)
    - Issues in Michigan 1990-1996 (Box 3)
    - Issues at University of Michigan
      - 1989-1990 (Box 3)
      - 1991-1996, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Computer Bulletin Discussion re: bisexuality 1993 (Box 3)
  - Conferences
    - "What To Do About Nine and Two: Organizing To Ensure Lesbian-Gay-Bisexual Rights," March 27, 1993 (Box 3)
    - Treatment of Shame-based Syndromes," November 17, 1989 (Box 3)
  - Educational Outreach Program
    - Evaluations
      - 1981-1983 (Box 3)
      - 1992 (Box 3)
    - General Files 1976-1980 (Box 3)
    - Academic Program Development circa 1995 (Box 3)
  - Fraternities 1988-1991 (Box 4)
  - Gays in the Military 1991 (Box 4)
  - Housing Issues circa 1990-1993 (Box 4)
  - Leadership Award, Queer Unity Project 1996 (Box 4)
  - Michigan Campaign for Human Dignity 1993-1994, 4 folders (Box 4)
  - Newsletter
    - July-September 1995 (Box 4)
    - May-June 1995 (Box 4)
    - January 1996 (Box 4)
    - June-September 1996, 4 folders (Box 4)
    - January-November 1997 (Box 4)
  - Pamphlets and Flyers 1994-1995 (Box 4)
  - Resources, miscellaneous 1994-2001 (Box 4)
  - Resources Center, miscellaneous circa 2001 (Box 4)
  - Same Sex Housing at University of Michigan circa 1991 (Box 4)
  - Same Sex Marriage/Benefits 1988-1996 (Box 4)
  - Self Evaluation Form for Resource People 1985 (Box 4)
  - Training Manual 1994 (Box 4)
  - University of Michigan and Michigan Contact Lists circa 1994 (Box 4)
  - Various Surveys and Questionnaires undated (Box 4)
  - Women's Study Program circa 1990 (Box 4)
  - Workshop Requests 1993-1996, 2 folders (Box 4)
- Audio-Visual Materials
  The Audio-Visual Material series, 1987-2001 (1.25 linear feet), is comprised of audio recordings, photographs, posters, and video recordings. The thirty audio recordings include copies of the WCBN broadcasts of the Gay/Lesbian Radio Collective Show. The broadcasts date from the 1987-1988 time period. Other audio recordings include the March on Washington, October 13, 1987 and Coming Out Stories, dated October 20 and 27, 1987. The photographs are mainly 4 x 6 prints. Unfortunately, most of the photographs are unidentified and the majority are undated. The posters include twelve posters used to showcase office events on campus. The posters are largely undated. The video recordings include two VHS tapes. The video recordings include a taping of an Ann Arbor City Council Meeting held on November 4, 1991, that discusses the Domestic Partnership Ordinance, and "The African-American Lesbian Experience: A Personal and Historical Perspective." The latter recording was taped as part of the 1994 Martin Luther King, Jr. Symposium held at the University of Michigan.
  - Photographs
    (mainly 4 x 6 prints)
    - Lesbian Rights Now, March on Washington 1993 photograph by Keary Campbell (Folder 1)
    - Miscellaneous circa 1994-1996 (Box 4)
    - Community Celebration 1994 (Box 4)
    - Library Dedication 1994 (Box 4)
    - LGBT Office, miscellaneous undated (Box 5)
    - Parade Celebration 1994 (Box 5)
    - Unidentified prints 1995-2001
      - 1995, 1 folders (Box 5)
      - 1996, 1 folders (Box 5)
      - 1997, 1 folders (Box 5)
      - 2001, 1 folders (Box 5)
    - Unidentified and undated prints, 4 folders (Box 5)
  - Video tapes
    - Ann Arbor City Council, Taping of the Domestic Partnership Ordinance November 4, 1991, VHS (Box 5)
      (original shown on Ann Arbor Community Access Television)
    - "The African-American Lesbian Experience: A Personal and Historical Perspective," filmed as part of Martin Luther King Jr. Symposium January 17, 1994, VHS (Box 5)
  - Audio recordings
    - Bisexuality undated, Cassette (Box 5)
    - Blue and Mark (?) December 29, 1987, Cassette (Box 5)
    - Boyce, Jerome undated, Cassette (Box 5)
    - Civil Disobedience undated, Cassette (Box 5)
    - Coming Out Stories October 27, 1987 and Billie Edwards, October 20, 1987, Cassette (Box 5)
    - French, Felicia undated, Cassette (Box 5)
    - Gallagher, Helen September 15, 1987, Cassette (Box 5)
    - Gay Games, Celebration 90 January 1989, Cassette (Box 5)
    - Gay/Lesbian Radio Collective Show (WCBN), Cassette
      - Dooley's 1987 (Box 5)
      - First Anniversary Show March 1988 (Box 5)
      - Martin, Terry undated (Box 5)
      - #1 and #2 May 19, 1987, May 26, 1987 (Box 5)
      - #3 and #4, (includes Elaine Noble) June 9, 1987 (Box 5)
      - #6 June 23, 1987 (Box 5)
      - #5 and #8 June 16, 1987, July 7, 1987 (Box 5)
      - #7 June 30, 1987 (Box 5)
      - #9 July 14, 1987 (Box 5)
      - #10 and 11 July 21, 1987, July 28, 1987 (Box 5)
      - #13 and #14 August 11, 1987, August 18, 1987 (Box 5)
    - Homosexuals Anonymous March 1988 and Billie Edwards April 1988, Cassette (Box 5)
    - Ladies Against Lesbians, Judy Levy undated, Cassette (Box 5)
    - LAGROC/MSA, Code and Bylaw January 19, 1988, Cassette (Box 5)
    - Legislating Sexuality March 11, 1994, 2 Cassettes (Box 5)
    - March on Washington October 13, 1987, Cassette (Box 5)
    - Ozone House August 25, 1987 and Jim Toy, September 1987, Cassette (Box 5)
    - Street People Gay Youth May 24, 1988, Cassette (Box 5)
    - Take Back the Night, April 19, year not indicated, Cassette (Box 5)
    - Thompson, Karen September 20, 1987, Cassette (Box 5)
    - Unidentified tape undated (Box 5)
  - Posters
    - Miscellaneous events, (12) undated (Folder 1)
- Ted Fredley Files [Restricted access]
  The Ted Fredley Files (1 linear foot) series includes materials collected to or pertaining to the life of Ted Fredley of Orchard Lake, Michigan. Fredley, who identified as queer, was an activist for the fair treatment of LGBT individuals and extensively corresponded with others in the community, religious leaders, and corporations. The series contains selections of Fredley's correspondence between 1983 and 2005, discussing both personal matters and broader issues in the LGBT world, as well as materials printed by gay publications in the Midwest and across the United States. Access to the Series is restricted.
  - AOL (Box 6)
    [Closed]
  - Clippings, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Correspondence
    - Undated (Box 6)
    - Chats, 1996-1997 (Box 6)
    - Emails, 1996-2005 (Box 6)
    - Formal (Box 6)
    - Personal
      - 1983-1985 (Box 6)
      - 1985-1987 (Box 6)
      - 1988-1989 (Box 6)
      - 1990-1997 (Box 6)
  - Personal papers, 4 folders (Box 6)
  - Printed materials (Box 6)
  - Publications, 2 folders (Box 6)